[Music]
hello
everyone welcome to the 25th live
episode of the ask a budget show and the
abhijit chapter podcast
so today we discuss geopolitics in world
history and
as usual we have a wonderful bunch of
questions that we've lined up
but before i begin i need to thank you
all
so the abhijit chavda podcast has now
broken into the top 100 list
in india in spotify it's yesterday it
was on 98.
today it's in the 88th position so i
need to
thank you all thank you very much for
making this happen
uh we are crossing some very interesting
milestones
so it's great so thank you once again
thank you everyone and now let's begin
with the podcast with this session
and let's start with question number one
so yatinder asks after world war
ii the powerful nations took a step
towards global peace by establishing the
united nations
but is it really doing any good to us at
the moment
when we can clearly see some nations
using the
dirty tactics to achieve their goals
causing human suffering
and global chaos how can it be
strengthened further i
assume you mean the united nations thank
you
yes so after the second world war the
united nations was established
and this is a hierarchical organization
it has a u.n security council in which
you have five permanent members
so this organization was set up to
consolidate
the power that the winning side
had acquired after the second world war
the
aim of this organization is to ensure
global order
or rules based system global peace etc
but on the
terms of the winners of the second world
war
so it the so ostensibly the the
the role of the united nations is to uh
maintain global peace and global order
etc but its real purpose
is to entrench the winning side of the
second world war world war
in power and that's why you have seen we
can see that there has been absolutely
no reforms
in the u.n over the past 70 years after
the world war ii ended
right i mean the u.n security council
has certain member states that are
basically lightweights today
they don't deserve to be on the
permanent membership of the security
council and they still hold their veto
power
so this all reflects the global order as
it was
in 1945 this is basically obsolete but
the
but the countries that have the power
they are trying to hang on to that and
they are opposing
any uh reform or any proposal to reform
the u.n security council
or the united nations now it's
interesting that india was
offered a permanent position on the u.n
security council
twice in 1950 and 1955
our prime minister mr nero rejected both
these offers
and insisted that china be given the
position instead and today china is the
is in power i mean it's it's on the
permanent
uh it's a permanent member of the un
security council it has the power of
veto
and it is preventing india from ever
becoming a permanent member there so
basically the role of the un
is well it is to entrench the
interests in the in the positions of the
five countries
the five winning powers after second
world war that is the real
intention see whenever you have a
multilateral organization
it essentially has one agenda and that
agenda is decided by the
most powerful nation or small group of
nations in this organization
and you see this everywhere you see it
in the shanghai cooperation organization
you see it in brics you see it in nato
you see it in g7 g8 whatever it is
g20 etc and you see it in the un
the who unesco etc all these
organizations
have a stated purpose but they also have
a certain agenda
that is that of the most powerful nation
in the organization
so that's what it is today now today you
can see that the chinese have
infiltrated deep into the u.n and
they're controlling vital
uh bureaucratic positions etc now
bureaucratic positions look
like they are they seem very boring and
mundane but they are the ones
that basically decide the rules and and
all the uh the policies etc of the
organization
so the chinese have steadily over the
last two or three decades
infiltrated deep into the u.n and now
they occupy positions of power
everywhere
india has never had this ambition and
that's why india is basically left
behind
as of today so the main purpose of the
un
is to further the agenda of the most
powerful nations in the u.n
that's the thing about any organization
so that's what you see right now
the u.n basically um it doesn't it
doesn't have any any power to enforce
any rules because you see the you yeah
the united states
basically flouts u.n resolutions and u.n
uh
views from time to time and so does
china
so these resolutions are non-binding
they don't really the un doesn't really
have the power to
enforce any of these things and that's
why you see nations
using a variety of tactics like you said
dirty tactics etc
to achieve their goals and it does cause
human suffering global chaos when we
don't have a great deal of global chaos
but there's a great deal of human
suffering
that is being uh that is being caused by
the
vested interests and agendas of certain
powerful nations you see that all the
time
so the u.n basically needs a great deal
of reforms it needs to be reformed if it
is to really have any real legitimacy in
the eyes
of the world the purpose it serves is
very different from what was its
original
stated purpose that's why it is
important that this
organization be reformed but as we know
the entrenched powers the five
entrenched powers will not allow that to
happen
so so it's an interesting phase we are
in right now that
the chinese are emerging the us is
waning to to some extent
so the us the u.n sorry is now
slowly becoming engaged in
an instrument of the chinese in
furthering their global ambitions
so that's what we see today
harsh asks what type of lifting
technology did
ancient civilizations use for all these
megalithic structures such as pyramids
temples and astronomical observatories
which are all made with huge granite and
basalt rocks
with millimeter precision not to mention
that bane's taking in beautiful carvings
that we have never been able to recreate
with the same
materials it's a very good question so
the carvings and all that we can
understand
it's it's definitely possible to for the
human ingenuity
ingenuity and skills to create beautiful
and painstaking carvings
even on a very large scale the real
question is how do you
move enormous blocks of granite maybe
several tons tens tens of tons maybe
hundreds of tons
you have the great temple at balbic the
the ancient roman temple
which probably was a pre-roman temple as
well
and you have one block of is it granite
it's a it's one block of rock there
which weighs over 100 tons it's almost
impossible to move that even today with
modern technology
so how did the ancients of that region
move such enormous uh rocks
such enormous blocks of granite or any
kind of rock and we don't see any
evidence of how they moved it
and again in the pyramids these are
enormous gigantic monumental
structures and in each block that these
pyramids
are made of these are very very large
blocks they weigh a lot
and the only conceivable way these
egyptians would have
constructed the pyramids was by was by
constructing
ramps of on a very large scale
so that you could move the blocks along
these ramps but you don't see
any evidence of these ramps because such
ramps themselves will be monumental
structures
so it's a big mystery there are many
such places where you have
monumental architecture enormous
blocks made out of rock and there's no
evidence of how these blocks were moved
so that is one of the enduring mysteries
of history we do not have an
answer as of today now some people go
into this what's that called
the uh the the theory that aliens helped
us to do this
well if you have such a theory you need
to present some sort of evidence
as of today there is zero evidence of
any alien involvement
so without evidence a theory is just a
hypothesis it
does not need to be taken seriously if
you have a theory
that doesn't provide any evidence then
you can dismiss that theory without any
evidence
that's how it works so uh forgetting
let's forget about the alien angle the
alleged alien angle there's no such
thing there's no evidence for that
but even if we discount that there is
this is a big mystery because even today
it's extremely difficult
with modern 21st century technology and
machines and all that
to move such enormous rocks so this is
an interesting question you bring up
harsh
as of today we do not have an answer no
historian no archaeologist
has been able to satisfactorily answer
the question
as to how these enormous blocks of rock
were moved
and placed into position with such
incredible
precision there's not even a gap of a
millimeter like you say yes it is true
so this is an enduring mystery
shubham asks do you think that religion
acts as a barrier
in developing a nation as we see most of
the countries with
atheist majority or good percentage of
people
who follow no religion uh such countries
are developed or fast growing
for example china scandinavian countries
and other european nations
what is your take in this sir so if you
look at the history of europe and the
history of the scandinavian nations
these nations
have until recently being been very much
christian
right so therefore you cannot say that
because of atheism
that's the the atheism is propelling the
growth of these nations
these nations until very very recently
have been christian majority nations
china has always been a confusion taoist
with this nation
right now you are right china has
developed a lot over the past century
ever since the communist came into place
that is true
but my point is that it all depends on
the kind of
religion you're talking about you cannot
categorize all religions
under the same blanket all religions are
not the same sir please understand this
please repeat this after me
of all religions are not the same
and for example the dharmic religions
are not even religions
because they don't have one god and one
prophet and one book
right so if you take the dharmic
religions for example
let's take the example of japan japan is
a
dharmic nation they are very proud of
their buddhist and
and shinto heritage this is a
polytheistic
culture and this is a very traditional
culture japan is very proud of its
polytheistic
and and ancient roots and japan has
never
abandoned its culture its religions
its mix its very beautiful syncretic mix
of religions
shintoism and buddhism right most
japanese practice
some form of religion very few are
atheists
and yet japan is the most
technologically advanced nation in the
world
and the reason people are so drawn to
japan
is because of this incredible mixture of
tradition and modernity
right so japan is a shining example of
how
you can be the most technologically
advanced
nation in the world and yet be very
proud of
your culture and your religion and of
your religious roots and you keep
practicing that
right so japan is an example of what
india can become
so i disagree with uh the notion that
many people
have that religion is a barrier towards
developing a nation
religion is a barrier depending on which
religion it is for example
if you look at the dark ages of europe
ask yourself
what caused this these dark ages why
were
why was knowledge banned why was any
form of science banned why was
questioning
the or the prevailing dogma band who did
this there's only one authority which
did this and that is the catholic church
that is why europe was so deep into
superstition
and and uh and it was so backward
during the medieval ages the dark ages
etc all the ancient
knowledge the pre-christian europeans
had all the ancient european
indo-european culture
and and wisdom and the knowledge of
basically it was ayurveda the herbal
knowledge and all that and the
astronomical knowledge all of that was
destroyed
it was wiped out all the books were
burned all the people who practiced this
were
murdered in in great numbers there were
crusades within europe itself
aimed at stamping out every trace of the
pre
pre-christian culture and science and
knowledge
in europe yeah and you had these
horrific
inquisitions and witch hunts that that
basically the only aim was to uh
secure the supremacy of the catholic
church all across europe
so that is an example of a religion
acting as a barrier in developing
a a people or any kind or or
any country so that's a shining example
of that
now in the case of dharmic religions
hinduism buddhism whatever you call them
jainism etc if you look at ancient
india india ancient india was always the
most scientifically
and technologically advanced
civilization of its time
whether it's the harappan phase the
pre-harappan phase the post-harappan
phase
the mauryan phase the gupta phase
basically everything that happened
before the past 1000 years india was
always at the forefront of science
technology and knowledge mathematics
everything
india developed all the sciences all the
mathematics the
the calculus everything trigonometry
astronomy pharmacology toxicology
everything that you can imagine
that you can imagine which basically is
the foundation
that was that gave rise to modern
science the
contributions of india are completely
unacknowledged which is a different
story
but here is an example of
if you call hinduism religion then this
has
fostered this development of science and
technology
and therefore i need to strongly put
this point across that it all depends on
the kind of religion we are dealing with
if all religions are not the same dharma
is not i mean certain religions are not
even dharma basically okay
dharma is only what is the four
so-called religions that come under the
dharmic category hinduism buddhism
secretism and jainism
everything else is technically it is a
dharma
understand that please all right so
only means these four broad categories
everything else is not dharma it is
essentially a dharma
so every religion is not the same
certain religions
are a significant impediment in the
development of a country and a people
and certain religions actually actively
promote that
so you can see the example of ancient
india you can see the example of
japan today which is way more advanced
than china or the scandinavian countries
right so i hope this answers
this question which is a very good
question
akash asks why did the french revolution
stabilize france and made it prosp and
make it prosper but on the other hand
russia after the russian revolution
started starving and killing its own
people
and finally crumbled in the 1990s so am
i right in saying that france prospered
after the french
revolution which is an interesting thing
so the french revolution
well revolutions are violent affairs
and revolutions most often
do more harm than good so what was the
aim
of the french revolution liberty
which means secularism right liberty
equality
fraternity and secularism so yes the aim
of the french revolution was to
overthrow the monarchy
they did succeed in doing that in a very
bloody manner and lots of collateral
damage
lots of violence lots of unnecessary
deaths and all that you had
in the french revolution it was a period
of great chaos whatever geopolitical
gains the french had done had made over
the
past centuries were all frittered away
because of this
disastrous turmoil within france
and then what happened within a very
short period of time
monsieur napoleon bonaparte mr napoleon
he convinced the french people
that the only way to take forward the
gains of the french revolution and the
ideals and the principles of the french
revolution
was to crown him the emperor of france
isn't that funny that's the kind of
audacity this man had
so in a very short period of time you
had a return to monarchy
of course napoleon was a secularist he
did
reform this the the system of governance
thoroughly completely totally overhauled
it
the system that france uses today for
governance is basically the napoleonic
code
and the constitution also is very
napoleon's constitution was also very
influential
so yes there was a great change in
france and
france was able to uh
to to continue developing as a nation
after the revolution but it was a very
big
uh period of turmoil and chaos now if
you look at the russian revolution
uh it was in 1917
yeah 17 18 thereabouts so the russian
revolution
also aimed at that the same it had the
same aim as the french revolution
to overthrow the monarchy the tars right
and that's what they achieved
and it was all about empowering the the
the proletariat overthrowing the
bourgeoisie and
having a people's revolution and the
people's dictatorship etc
which they were able to achieve so once
again you had
uh the the royals were massacred
they were all shot and the old system
was
thrown out and then you had the soviet
police bureau
that took over and embarked upon this
imperialistic
process and so what what was the
end result of this you had a very small
number of people the politburo who
came to power and who basically ruled
this vast
nation right so you can call it whatever
you want we can call it
the dictatorship of the proletariat or
you could call it the people's republic
or the united the ussr union of soviet
socialist republics
but it was again a very small number of
people a small clique
a small gang of people a small cabal
who had all the power so how is it
different from a monarchy
so once again you had a so the thing is
this
you can never have absolute equality in
any human society
if you have an ordered society you have
a hierarchy
so it always gives rise to another
hierarchy that's what happens
these revolutions and all they always
give rise to another hierarchy and
another
consolidation of power with us people
having them
having most of the power now russia also
developed a lot
after the russian revolution it became a
superpower i mean come on
did they starve and kill their own
people yes mr stalin did kill a lot of
people
via artificial famines but after stalin
you had
i mean the situation was better of
course it was
the entire country was ruled with an
iron hand for sure
but you know what it's the same
everywhere
you you are in in democratic systems you
are made to think that
you have the right to vote etc but
everything is controlled anyway
right so yes the soviet system did
crumble in the 1990s
and then you have a return to the to the
uh
to the monarchy of sorts mr putin is the
new tsar he could say
he calls him i mean mr xi jinping is the
new emperor
right you can call it by call this
position by whatever name you want
but it's a return to the same system so
revolutions
are a violent chaotic process they have
some
some good results some good outcomes
some bad outcomes i think overall
the french overall prospered more i
would say
than the russians russia has always been
a hard land
in the history of russia if you look at
the past 1000 years it's always been a
history of hardships so it is so
whatever happened after the russian
revolution
is essentially part of the same pattern
that russia is a hard hard land to live
in
the story of russia is one of hardships
so
every nation has a certain character the
russian character is that
it's it's a land of hardships it's a
land of sorrows
and it's a land of hard people people
who drink vodka who are stoic
and who carry on no matter what happens
so that's the character of russia and
that's what you see there
and the french have a very different
character and that's what you see there
as well
so that is a small brief comparison i
mean these
these are vast topics you can spend 10
years
studying the russian revolution and the
french revolution
i've just given a very brief overview so
that's a small brief
comparison of these two events
cyton gopa asks does tibet count
in the core of the india china
relationship or part of the india
china relationship which is the way
forward for the tibetan issue
in the india china relationship in my
perspective
well whether it is acknowledged or not
tibet is always there
tibet is the central issue in the
india-china relationship
india and china have never been
neighbors in the past two and a half
thousand years ever since china
was born china was born about two and a
half thousand years ago as a
civilization or a nation or a culture
and india and china have never been
neighbors until
the chinese annexation of tibet the
illegal chinese annexation occupation of
tibet in 1955
at the hands of the chinese communist
party and that is the first time
that india and china have become
neighbors of sorts and
that's the first time india and china
have entered into a conflict so the key
to resolving this
from our perspective from the indian
perspective and from the tibetan
perspective
is freedom from for tibet tibet needs to
be restored to freedom and the chinese
know this
the chinese know that the tibet issue is
the core of the india china problem
even though india and china never speak
about it china keeps talking about the
one china policy and india doesn't
really comment about it
but the core issue and the key to
resolving the problem
is tibet so india needs to have
a more proactive more more long-term
uh indian need to have proper long-term
vision for how it wants to resolve this
matter
india needs to resolve this in a matter
in a manner that is advantageous to
india as well as to the people of tibet
and the tibetans also need to take
certain steps for example you have the
tibetan government in exile
and you have his holiness holiness dalai
lama
who lives in dharamshala now mr the the
his holiness the dalai lama needs to uh
basically announce what is his plan
for reincarnation see the process is
that when the dalai lama
passes on when he dies he is
reincarnated somewhere in tibet
and there are certain signs that the
llamas have to look for and then they
they travel all across tibet and then
until they find
a newborn child or a child who was born
after the passing of the previous dalai
lama who exhibits certain signs and
certain auspicious omens etc
and then that child is taken as the next
dalai lama
he is tutored in the ways of buddhism
and culture and all that and eventually
this child becomes the next dalai lama
so that is what his holiness the present
the current dalai lama
underwent as a child so now
whether we like it or not his holiness
is very old now he must be in his 80s
now
so it's it may be a question of another
another 20 years
20 25 30 years if he lives long i wish
he does
but in the next two three decades he
will unfortunately pass on and
he needs to announce his plans for his
reincarnation he needs to announce
whether he will be reincarnated in
whether he will be reincarnated in tibet
or whether he will be reincarnated
in india or somewhere else within the
tibetan community
because the chinese plan to hijack the
office of the dalai lama
and appoint their own dalai lama so if
his holiness the dalai lama announces
that he will not be reincarnated in
tibet he will be reincarnated
reincarnated either in india or
somewhere else then the chinese claim to
the
legitimacy of their appointees the dalai
lama will
evaporate so this is one step that
we need to do we need to take the indian
government and
the dalai lama need to work together on
this and there needs to be a statement
because we cannot allow the chinese to
hijack this
most sacred office and this is currently
the highest position in the buddhist
world and one of the highest positions
in the entire dharmic world
so we cannot allow the chinese communist
party to hijack
this very ancient tradition so that's
one thing that's new that needs to be
done
and secondly india needs to find
a long-term india needs to have a
long-term vision on a long-term plan
over the next 20 30 years in which tibet
can be freed from the
clause of the chinese communist party
because the key to
to a lot of things the key to to
securities
stability prosperity and peace on
india's northern boundary
is the freedom of tibet if tibet becomes
free then all the issues go away
and we will even have a land route to
to northern asia and to to the to the
west through tibet
et cetera so these are things that are
very important to india's long-term
national security
and to india's long-term future and
the tibetans are our own people
ethnically they may be different but
they are part of our own culture
they are very close to us culturally
right they are part of the
sphere you could say we've always had
the best of relations
relationship with the tibetan people for
centuries for almost 2000 years ever
since tibet
came into being in any way so
that's what needs to be done india needs
to take this very seriously
india needs to have a long-term uh
vision and plan for this for that you
need political
continuity in india india's democracy
unfortunately is such that
there is no political continuity if the
result of the next election is it is
different
and some other party comes to power then
they will reverse all the policies
that are currently being implemented by
the current uh governing party
so that is india's major problem
india lacks political stability
and india's some of india's political
parties are outright anti-national
and they are basically in the pockets
and on the payroll of outside forces so
that is these are the issues
these are the challenges that india
needs to
mitigate soon soon i mean urgently
something needs to happen about this
something needs to be done
the national interest has to
supersede any constitution any
federalism
any democracy any laws that were passed
70 years ago
it doesn't matter what the constitution
says the constitution is a man-made
thing
the geography of india bharat wash is a
god-gifted thing
so we need to put that above any
constitution any laws
any rules any such thing india needs to
put its national interest
its long-term national interest at the
forefront change the constitution if you
need to
bring in a new constitution if you need
to it doesn't matter
the national interest in the
civilizational interest has to be
paramount
so india needs to india needs a leader
or leaders who have the fortitude to do
this
that's what india awaits
all right next question will the future
chinese currency
be used can the future chinese i mean
can the chinese currency
the yuan be used as a medium of exchange
in the future for global trade instead
of dollars
are current are the countries that are
currently suffering from u.s sanctions
looking for an alternative currency for
their international trade good question
very good question
it's all about these uh these networks
of power and and the currency
the uh the currency thing is a very
important part of this so
the global currency is is as of today
the us dollar
and that is what gives the united states
so much leverage
leverage globally that is one of the
things that underpins its status as a
superpower
that the us dollar is accepted without
question worldwide
even in places like north korea this
they do value u.s dollars
even the chinese have enormous reserves
of the u.s dollar right
so yes is one of the problems that that
many countries face when they come under
u.s sanctions
the fact that the us dollar is the
global currency
or de facto global currency works
against them so they do seek an
alternative
the russians in the past tried to make
try to do that with the ruble
today the chinese are trying to uh bring
the yuan
to that status uh via various
organizations and
and instruments such as the the brics
bank
and and other such things
so yes there is currently this tussle
going on
even the eu wants the euro to become one
of the major currencies it is one of the
major currencies but
uh no none of these currencies has the
status of the of the us dollar
so as long as the u.s dollar is the de
facto global currency
the us can run its writ throughout the
world so that is what the chinese
want to push back against they are
working
very hard very assiduously 24x7 to
in the direction of making the chinese
yuan
uh come near the status attain the
status
of a global currency so yes and the
other thing is cryptocurrency
so that's also one of the new things and
the chinese are cracking down on
cryptocurrency
they are not happy about the emergence
of the cryptocurrencies such as the
uh such as bitcoin etc because it uh
basically hinders their plan to make
their currency
the new the future global currency so
there is this very interesting
tussle going on right now very
interesting
how did uh the viking age suddenly stop
and how did they change europe and
the world that's a good question so the
viking age was basically from the
end of the eighth century to the middle
or the end of the 11th
century so that's how it was it's about
300 years or so that that is considered
to be the viking age
and so so who are the vikings the
vikings were the people of scandinavia
let me show you what it means
here's the map so let's go westwards
so the scandinavian countries are
denmark norway sweden and to some extent
finland
so the vikings were the danes the
norwegians and the swedes
they are basically one people one
culture one ethnicity
so these guys were mostly farmers
and they would engage in fishing
expeditions and some small raiding
expeditions to other lands but in the
late
late 9th century onwards
late 8th century onwards they began to
embark upon these raiding expeditions in
in
great force and very soon they overran
much of the
much of the island of the use of the
present-day united kingdom etc
especially the northern part and they
had a great deal of influence
in other parts of the world as well that
stretched all the way
to constantinople presently turkey
and they traded everywhere they they
controlled
various trade routes various various
river trade routes etc
and all that right so that is the viking
age that is what is known as the viking
age they were great conquerors
they conquered most of england and all
and they were basically polytheists they
were adherents to of the
old indo-european culture there if you
look at the pantheon of their gods
it is the same as the vedic pantheon
with different names
their greatest god thor is essentially
indra
so that is what the vikings were what
ended the viking age very simple
it is the christianization of the
vikings that ended
the viking age the christianization of
the vikings meant that they
accepted the the supremacy of the
catholic church
not just in religious matters but also
in political matters
and once they became christians they
lost the will to fight they lost their
that
inner fire etc and they became
one of the many christian states
that you will find across europe so
basically
in very short to answer your question it
is the christianization
of the scandinavian countries that ended
the viking age
okay there are two questions about sport
is performance in sports a good measure
of how ambitious a country
is that's asked by ashwathama the second
question is by pritham
does sports play any role in making a
country powerful or well known
yes there are a few things about sports
first of all
the uh a nation's sporting prowess
is a very good indicator of its overall
development
so you will find that countries with
high living standards and high
high levels of development they always
do well in sports and the reason is that
when people have excess money they have
good lives they have good living
standards and a good lifestyle
then they can spend time and energy on
leisure and on non-earning activities
and sports is a prime example of that so
if you
if you're only uh if you if the only
thing you're engaged in in life is to
make sure you don't starve then you have
to only think of that and you don't have
the time
or the money or the energy or the
nutrition to engage in sports and that's
what you have seen
for decades in india and secondly if the
government system is such that
if it is a if it if it basically
deprives the people
of various things then again you will
say that sports suffers
so that's why sports is a very good
indicator of the health of a country
of the per capita gdp of a country of
the overall living standards
and the overall levels of development of
a country
it also is an indicator of how ambitious
a country is
because you see that these these
socialist and marxist
and communist countries in the 19 in the
20th century where the ussr east germany
and the soviet bloc republics eastern
europe they all spent
millions or billions of dollars in
in creating a world-class world-class
sporting system and infrastructure and
they it was
imperative for them to be the number one
uh country in the olympics especially
for the ussr
and they basically they broke the rules
for that
they indulged in doping and drugs
and it ruined many the lives of many
athletes but it did not matter it was
national pride about everything else
so it is an indicator of how ambitious a
country is
and the thing about sports is that it
unifies a country it brings everyone
together
sporting success always raises the
morale of a country in the overall
confidence levels of a country
and that is why it tells you a lot about
the
various uh nairuvian and post-naruvian
regimes in india that they did not ever
care about sports
because they had no interest in raising
the morale or or the confidence
or the living standards of the country
but you will see
that over the past 20 years india has
started doing well in sports slowly
gradually right
india was the worst performing country
of all time in the olympics
but now every time you get more and more
medals
you even get gold medals once in a while
which
was unheard of in the past so this is an
indicator of the
rising standards slowly rising standards
living standards etc and and prosperity
levels in india
the current the government is still
doing nothing for it i mean
maybe the past maybe the current
government has invested a little bit in
sports but india's sporting
organizations are still extraordinarily
corrupt
you look at hockey look at football i
mean just two examples at random
so yes sports is very important for a
country
it increases a country's prestige it
increases a country the population's
overall confidence
and and sense of pride in being whoever
you are
being indian etc so yes it is a very
good indicator and it is important that
governments should spend a
good amount of money in developing
sports and sports develop
the sporting prowess or the sporting
ability of a country
develops automatically once the living
standards rise so it is a very good
indicator of the overall
health and condition of any country so
this is a very good question sir
akash asks the battle of thermopylae has
been very popular since the movie 300
where it was shown that all the spartan
soldiers were exceptional fighters
and that they were the best warriors the
world has ever seen
they were the only greek state that
stood against zexis
etc contrary to this i read something
totally
opposite what's the truth about this
battle and the spartan society overall
look um the western
world especially hollywood and the
americans they have been obsessed with
sparta for quite some time
basically the the western world
considers greece and rome to be the
birthplace of western civilization
along with to some extent babylon and
the middle east because of the
somatic religions and to some extent
egypt as well but
mainly it's it's uh greece and rome if
you look at the american express the
logo of american express
the erstwhile long-term logo it's it's
that of a roman centurion
of a greek hoplite soldier right spartan
hoplite soldier
so yes they've been obsessed with this
and they have see the movie i haven't
seen them
i i think i saw the movie 300 wasn't a
great movie
but yeah it portrays the spartans as the
ones who stood against the greeks
which is not really true the it was not
actually
the actual uh composition of the of that
war was
700. so there was an entire greek army
that stood against this invading persian
army that was
commanded by their great emperor
kshayarsha who is
called as xerxes in the west his real
name was
shayarsha it's a sanskrit name so
shayarsha invaded greece uh and
the greeks stood against that for some
time and then
you had a coalition of 700 soldiers it
was a it was an
alliance of greek city-states that stood
against
the greeks so the main army was sent
back to defend greece
and these 700 men stood and tried to
uh defend this pass the hot passes
thermopylae
against the invading persians as long as
they could in order to buy some time for
their main
main army to organize the defense of the
country so it was essentially a suicide
mission
their intention was to die after
defending as long as they could
so this was an alliance of greek
city-states
you had sparta yes the king leonidas was
the
commander or the leader of these 700 men
but you had
sparta you had arcadia corinth thieves
mycenae locris
et cetera so it was an it was a big
alliance and you had soldiers from all
these
various city states so it was not just
spartans historically spartans
were basically very militaristic
but they were known to retreat from a
battle
when it was not advantageous to them so
the
mythology that has been built up around
them is very misleading
they were good strategists they would
retreat
and run from a battle if they needed to
if it was suitable for them
strategically or tactically
right and and it's interesting that the
persian army
also had a very cosmopolitan composition
you had uh soldiers from persia of
course
but you had soldiers from media from
illum
from gandhara from india as well as from
skit here
so that is also interesting because the
at that time the portion empire did
incorporate the westernmost past
power regions or locations of india
so you had gandharan and indian soldiers
too in the army of triarsha
so it was a very interesting event it
was i think this battle took place
in 480 bce
and it is not 300 it is seven
approximately 700 men
so it's something that you should all
read about because the truth
is very different from what has been
portrayed in that movie
ford asks what is your stand on the
muslim community of india
what should they do to be a good
community for the country look my stand
on the muslim community is very clear
they are our people they are indians i
am very clear about this the muslims of
india pakistan sri lanka bangladesh
nepal
maldives afghanistan we are all one
people we have the same ancestors
all the muslims of this region have had
the same ancestors as all the hindus and
other people for at least 10 000 years
if not 20 30 50 000 years
so we are the same people the thing is
that the the culture and the religion
has changed
so what should the muslims do to be a
good community for the country well it's
for the muslims to decide who am i to
say
who are we to say the muslims have to
decide what is the best future path for
them
it is true that there is a great deal of
friction it is true i mean see that
which is ironic considering the fact
that
in 1857 in those muslims six everyone
lived together fought together and died
together and bled together for the
country
for the defense of the motherland even
during the azad
forge era in those muslim sex everyone
fought lived and bled together and died
together for the country for the mother
hand
for the motherland for the freedom of
the motherland so it's
it's unfortunate that we have this
friction today in this division because
it is
true that muslims and hindus live very
separate
lives in india it's like parallel
societies the muslims
unfortunately seem to feel that they
they
their their allegiance is somewhere else
some of them at least i would say many
of them there is this attitude among
muslims that we ruled over you for 800
years and
all that i mean come on you're not
foreigners
you are equally you're as much victims
as
the hindus were i mean your ancestors
and it's uh the thing is that it's all
politicized
after 1857 you had the british
engineering these
schisms in indian society and you had
these muslim organizations and muslim
scholars who were promoted by the
british
and by mr mohandas gandhi during the
caliphate movement
right khalafa movement etc so this gave
rise to this so-called two-nation theory
it was all engineered by the british and
then
fortified by the congress party and the
muslim league and mr jinnah and mr
gandhi etc
and this has created this schism in
india divide and rule and you can see
the
consequences of that even today
so that is the situation that we are in
today
we have this schism in society it's like
parallel societies
so it is for the muslim people of india
to decide what they want what is the
best
future for them they are indian citizens
they have the same rights as indians
they are the
sons and daughters of this land it is
for them it is
it would be good for everyone to unite
together be indians
you may practice whatever religion you
want at home but
as as citizens of india we have to all
be together right
and this politicization of religion has
to stop
unfortunately we find that muslims have
always been used as vote banks
before independence after independence
as well
and it is for the muslims to decide
whether they want to be used like this
or not
i mean voting voting on religious lines
is
it defeats the purpose of democracy it
is one of the great drawbacks in
democracy that you can
have people of one religion all voting
in
the bloc for one political but it
doesn't matter what the political party
actually
actually intends for the country so
these are the challenges india is facing
these are the challenges the muslims of
india are facing
there is this the media creates these
perceptions of muslims being
marginalized and all that
which is absolutely untrue right
so i would say so my stand is very clear
the muslims
of the entire subcontinent are our
brothers and sisters they are the
descendants of our own ancestors they
are our own people
what is best for them they should decide
who
am i to say anything they should decide
and they should think about the country
what is best for the country i think
that should be the guiding principle
that's all
ishan asks can we see an anti-west
anti-nato alliance in the future in the
form of russia china
iran and pakistan alliance we are
already seeing it and there is one more
nation in the mix
which is turkey now it's strange that
turkey is officially
a member of the nato alliance and yet
they are now
disengaging from it and engaging in
certain geopolitical moves that are very
much
anti-nato for example they bought the
russian
s 400 missile defense system because of
which the americans cut them out of the
out of
the f-35 fighter jet
project so they are no longer allowed to
buy that fighter jet and and
they have clearly decided that acquiring
this defense missile defense system is
is more beneficial to them than
going into the f-35 program so yes we
are seeing the
emergence of this alliance it's
led by the chinese and the russians to
some extent
and the pakistanis are getting involved
in this
the iranians they have recently signed
this big agreement with the chinese
a long-term strategic agreement with the
chinese in which the chinese will
will invest i think 30 40 billion
dollars
or something like that in iran over the
next two three decades
so iran seems to be on its way towards
becoming a satellite
of china pakistan
is getting is already a satellite of
china pakistan is already a chinese
colony right
many central asian states are part of
this
the shanghai cooperation organization
involves certain
central asian states like kyrgyzstan
kazakhstan uzbekistan
i'm not sure exactly which states are
there but many of these states are there
etc
so there is this geopolitical
realignment that's happening it's
gathering pace
in this decade so we are already seeing
this alliance emerge this anti-nato
alliance emerge
so if you look at the geography of this
if you look at the geography this is
india
so china is a member of this alliance
it's the leader of this alliance
russia is because of because of the
anti-russian
stance the strongly anti-russian stance
of nato
russia is also now part of this alliance
most of these central asian states which
are essentially part of the
russian sphere of influence
they are part of the anti-nato alliance
to some extent at least
pakistan is very much now anti-nato iran
is anti-nato
afghanistan is soon going to fall into
this anti-nato bracket because it is
going to be taken over by the taliban
and i'll talk about that later and you
have turkey so you have this realignment
happening
and as you can see if myanmar is being
controlled by china
then even myanmar is part of that so
india is essentially
encircled on land
by an anti-nato anti-us anti-india
alliance and there is this
string of pearls thing which is being
built in the indian ocean region
so the chinese aim to encircle india
completely
that is what is being engineered right
now
so yes you are right this is already
happening
saurabh asks why iran
wants to kill israel while saudi arabia
and the uae real muslims have a soft
corner
towards saudi arabia the abraham accord
etc um iranians are converted ex-parsees
extra-austrians
then why do they hate israel more than
the real originator of his
of islam okay interesting question
see it's not about religion at all
religion is
just a pretext you're right the saudis
i mean arabia is where islam was born
and if you look at
the way the geopolitical moves that
saudi arabia is playing today
it is getting closer to israel it no
longer views israel
as a mortal adversary the abraham occurs
have happened
uae and israel have now opened
efficient official cordial diplomatic
relations
and the saudis are very much on the
verge of also
normalizing their ties with israel so
where does that leave you and why is it
so that's the question
so why are the saudis now very happy
let's look at the geography
here's iran here here is the arabian
peninsula
and here is this little country called
israel
so egypt has long had reasonably good
relationship
with the israelis and now the most of
the
sunni islamic world is normalizing its
relation
relationship with israel but iran is
still hell-bent on destroying
israel so what is the cause of this
that's a very good question
very good question it all has to do
with the geopolitical ambition of iran
and the geopolitical ambition of saudi
arabia so the saudis have never
had this expansionist agenda
all the saudis have ever wanted is to
live in peace
in saudi arabia and enjoy the incredible
profits that this oil
business is bringing in for them they
have the highest
one of the highest living standards in
the world the saudis don't do any work
they do go to offices and sit there and
play solitaire but there's no real work
being done in saudi arabia
or in the entire arabian peninsula all
the real work is done by
expatriates by the it used to be the
indians now it is the pakistanis and the
bangladeshis etc who do all the manual
work etc
nepalese too and filipinos so
the arabians don't do any work right
they just enjoy the free money that
that is flowing in from the sales of the
oil now
saudi arabia is in well it's facing a
crisis because the oil has been
discovered
in the united states the u.s has become
the world's largest producer of oil
so the future flow of this
unlimited cash is no longer guaranteed
that's why the saudi arabian
the saudis want to normalize relations
relations with
the neighborhood and and you know settle
things down
the iranians have a very different
geopolitical agenda
the iranians are an expansionist regime
the regime of the ayat allah's they
basically want to bring back the
accented empire the persian empire the
haksha manish empire
they have an expansionist agenda they
see themselves
as conquering the world one day that's
why they are hell-bent on
on acquiring nuclear weapons technology
that's why they are so
active geopolitically way beyond their
borders right
india has absolutely no influence
outside its borders
the iranians have far more influence
beyond their borders than india can ever
have
as of today or india is willing to have
today so the iranians have been
very vigorous and active geopolitical
players for a very long time
they have a much greater apatite for
risk and that's why
they see israel as one of the major
stumbling blocks
against their long-term geopolitical
ambitions because as long as this jewish
state exists there
especially a jewish state that has
nuclear weapons
then iran's long-term geopolitical
ambitions will never be fulfilled
especially when you have pakistan and
india next door who also have nuclear
weapons
so pakistan may one day maybe in the
next 50 or 100 years
reunite with india but iran wants to
basically take over the world and israel
is a big problem for them and so is
india actually
and so are the saudis so that is the
reason why they are hell-bent on
destroying israel
that is the real region reason it is not
about re it's not about religion
it's about their long-term geopolitical
ambitions
to rule the world
so man asks why are the afghan forces
unable to combat the taliban
in spite of training under nato forces
for more than a decade
is it due to a lack of willpower
lack of numbers or quality of weapons
okay let me give you a different example
the indians
have a very long military tradition for
thousands of years
india had the sixth the ra the the
rajputs
the jaats and
they almost defeated the british in
1857.
so what did the british do they
engineered
they they almost basically see the
india also had the marathas so the these
forces these native indigenous
indian forces reached re-established
hindu beast
over india by defeating the mughal
empire right
and the british saw what is the
capability of india
and how powerful india is how how much
how good the indian
soldiers are what is their great what is
the quality
it's the highest quality so what they
did was they starved india so that
indians can't fight
if you can't if you don't have food if
you're starving then how will you fight
so it is always about the resources that
you have the logistical
whether you have the logistics or not
that is what determines the quality of
your
fight of of how well you fight you know
the
old adage is that an army
fights on its stomach so if you don't
have
uh supplies then you can't fight
it it is true about supplies of food
it's true about supplies of ammunition
and many other things so the real
secret to any fighting forces success
is logistics it is the supply chains
are they being supplied with enough
cash with enough food do they have
access to water do they have access to
the right kind of weaponry do they have
sufficient ammunition
that is what determines whether an army
succeeds or fails you you may be the
best soldiers in the world
you may have you may be the bravest
soldiers in the world
but if you don't have the right
technology if you don't have the
resources if you don't have the supplies
then you are doomed to failure so the
nato
people have been training the afghan
forces for a decade or whatever
but what how much funding do the afghan
forces have
do they have sufficient weaponry do they
have sufficient
ammunition is does there exist a
sufficient amount of political willpower
to keep fighting taliban these are the
questions that will answer
why the afghan forces are unable
to combat the taliban the americans
have left it open by design the country
to the taliban the taliban now controls
more
regions of afghanistan than does the
afghan government
so the americans knew this was coming
they have been planning this
exit strategy for many years
right so that is why
the afghan forces are unable to combat
the taliban
they don't have enough weaponry they
don't have enough ammunition
they don't have enough funding and most
importantly the political will is waning
now
it's the writing is on the wall the
taliban is going to take over
but this time there's going to be a more
orderly day
by the taliban because several other big
forces are involved in this bigger
bigger fish are at play here
another question about the taliban
taliban is officially
neutral in the kashmir issue and they
want to have good relations with india
and even india wants to build the
chabahar port route through afghanistan
so what will be the afghan the india
afghanistan or taliban relationship in
the future
should india have official relationship
relations with the taliban
after the withdrawal of the u.s troops
see india's position
in afghanistan has to be dictated by the
long-term
national interest in the long term
india wants to regain land access to
afghanistan which
lies through pok pakistan occupied
kashmir india wants
a peaceful and stable afghanistan
through which it can
open a land route to
the rest of the world especially europe
right now india is cut off from the
whole of the world through land
and india would eventually like the
afghans to become
a friendly nation to the indians right
to india
so right now what's happening is this
see that the taliban is going to take
over afghanistan very soon the americans
have
declared that they are leaving at the
end of august
so by the end of august there will be
not a single american soldier left in
afghanistan
and the taliban is going to take over
most of afghanistan this time there may
not be so much chaos
because everything is being stage
managed by two or three
external countries so the keys
to the taliban lie in ravel pindi
which is the headquarters of the
pakistani army
but the keys to raval pindi lie in
beijing
because the chinese own the pakistan
army
so essentially the taliban who are a
proxy of pakistan are actually a proxy
of the chinese
now the chinese have long-term interest
in afghanistan
afghanistan is a means to see the
taliban is a means to an end for the
pakistanis
because they want influence in
afghanistan and pakistan is a means to
an end
for the chinese because they want
long-term influence
in pakistan in afghanistan and beyond
the chinese
have super power ambitions and they are
using these as stepping stones
towards reaching that super super power
status
and the chinese are interested in
afghanistan's resources there is a great
deal of
mining to be done in afghanistan there's
a great deal of copper for example
and other minerals and resources in
afghanistan and the chinese want to
exploit all of that
and that's why they want an orderly
transition
to to the taliban power in afghanistan
and the taliban will never ever do
anything against the chinese
for this reason so the chinese are
essentially stage managing everything
the russians are also very much involved
in this
and india is cut out of this entire
process now the taliban are
have they said they are neutral about
kashmir i'm not sure maybe they are
see the taliban also know that if
india so desires india can wipe out the
taliban
india does have the military capability
and where we thought that
afghanistan is a stone's throw away from
kashmir india can
very rapidly if it wants
basically take over p okay rush into
afghanistan
and in a couple of months if the
military objective is clear
it can basically annihilate the taliban
if it if it wants india can do it india
has the
military capability to do that so
taliban also
know this and that's why they are not
really
uh being so overly and
overtly antagonistic towards india so
india needs to right now bide its time
whatever investments india has made in
afghanistan right now are on the verge
of being lost
fine there are successes and failures in
geopolitics it's always about the
long-term game
so as of today india is cut out of
afghanistan after the afghan peace
process
the russians the chinese and the
pakistanis are deciding what's happening
there
let it be so be patient build your
capabilities
build your strength and when the time is
right
india needs to basically uh
play its role a major role in
afghanistan because
afghanistan needs to be brought back to
peace
and to stability it is it is beneficial
for india and it is beneficial for the
afghan
people as well so right now india
doesn't have much of a role to play
india is a bystander india is basically
reduced to watching what's happening
there
there is some i think some deal some
amount of uh
maybe some uh back channel communication
of some kind
it's always there so there is there is
some communication happening
at some levels between india and the
taliban most likely
it may not be made public but any
sensible country would do that and i
expect it is being done
so india needs to play the long term
game as of now when it comes to
afghanistan and the taliban
so akash asks is vogue culture really a
thing to consider
or is it something we can ignore good
question a voc culture is taking over
the
united states right now and much of the
western world so what is voc culture
voc culture is something that has
emerged in the vacuum left behind
after the fall of christianity
so you know in the past in the 1980s
when the when the pope
would visit any country in europe or in
the west there would be
hundreds of thousands of people lining
the streets waiting to catch a glimpse
of the pope
today when the pope visits some place
there's nobody on the streets
so that gives you an indication of the
decline of christianity and the way
people are rejecting christianity in the
west because now people
are becoming aware of the true history
of christianity that it is a
it has played a very major political
role in europe it has been the real
center of power
and it has well you can read up the
history of the popes
to understand the real role of
christianity so europe and the west have
woken
up to this they are leaving christianity
in in omas
now the thing is that christianity has
been the moral foundation
of the west for about a thousand years
of if not more
so every person needs
a moral foundation in their life a set
of moral principles to live by
because it is very difficult to think on
your own
about what is right what is wrong it's
people you know thinking is hard work
people don't like to think they like to
be told what to do
that's why they look up to leaders and
they need moral principles something
that is already
ready made for them that they can follow
and
because they are now realizing what
christianity truly is and because they
are leaving christianity so
in so many numbers they are left without
a moral
compass so they are left without
a rule book that will guide them in life
and the leftists have
jumped into this vacuum by giving them
this woke ideology
so woke ideology is about the about the
moral high ground
it's about doing the right thing etc but
the right thing is very distorted when
it comes to voc culture
it is all about identity politics it's
all about
uh empowering a certain
political ideology and that ideology
actually is marxism
it is cultural marxism which takes which
takes a
myriad number of forms it has a lot of
different manifestations
and voc culture is the latest
manifestation
of cultural marxism it's all about
dividing a society among various
identities
and creating this conflict between the
identities and it's all about
taking the moral high ground that my uh
my ideology is morally superior to yours
and therefore i can hit you
and you need to be marginalized and
cancelled and all that
and that is unfortunately now being
exported
to india so all these all these
misguided
students who study in all these various
universities jnu
and various other universities
especially in the humanities departments
they are all exposed
to this new vocal religion by these
professors
who are all marxist professors who all
follow the marxist ideology they're all
ideologues they're all
overground workers of the communist
course these professors
india has allowed them to take over the
academic system especially the
humanities
and that's why this is now being
exported to india and they are again
dividing india under
in in various classes it's all about
destroying hinduism
so you don't say hinduism you say
brahmanism in order to attack hinduism
because the brahman class was the
basically the
the people who had the knowledge who
were in charge of preserving india's
knowledge
so that is being attacked so that
india's knowledge disappears and
therefore you can undermine the
foundations of hinduism
and india's ancient culture and then
they create this class divided between
dalits and
various other people etc even this term
dalit is a very new term
it's all thanks to mr gandhi and later
it was taken up by the marxists
so this voc ideology this work culture
is now being exported into india
it is becoming a nuisance so that's
where we are
we need to take it very seriously we
cannot ignore it
and the the way to tackle it properly is
to reform the academic system
basically
what do i say the academic system needs
to be
uh decontaminated of its
marxist leanings which is throughout it
even the iits are full of these
humanities departments
which i've spoken about earlier so it's
all about basically uh
decontaminating and reforming india's
academic system
until that is done it's going to become
a bigger and bigger problem in india
the smoke culture
saurabh kumar asks there are high
speculations that china will try and
invade and capture taiwan soon
given that nato might help taiwan a
heavy
amount of military involvement from
china will be required on the eastern
end
do you think that would be the right
time for india to act on taking back
pok and aksai chin
also recently you mentioned that
balochistan might become part of india
very soon enough
what did you mean by this can you please
elaborate about this
see i have said this in the past i will
say it again india needs to stop
thinking about pok and execution india
needs to think bigger
india needs to organizational ambitions
india needs to think that needs to
have the ambition of becoming a
superpower in the next 20 years
if it india has that ambition then poke
and exercise will come back to india
automatically
pakistan also will eventually come back
to india and so will afghanistan
okay in due time not in the next five
months
or five years but in due time on a
geopolitical time scale of decades
we need to be stopping impatient we need
to stop thinking so small
that we want pok this little piece of
land back an exciting this little piece
of
land back we need to think much bigger
than this
and so then eventually balochistan
everything will come back
in due time now about china's invasion
impending invasion of taiwan let's take
a look
at the map so like always this here is
the island of taiwan china regards
taiwan as
a renegade province and china is
building up its logistics and
capabilities and naval
strength etc military strength missile
strength everything
diplomatic strength geopolitical
strength its comprehensive
national power with the aim of
sooner or later reintegrating taiwan
with china by military force so i think
this will definitely happen in this
decade
they will do it when they judge that the
time is right
by their calculations which is basically
when the u.s is no longer strong enough
to stop such a thing from happening
so they will do it then so what should
india's response be
that is the main question here is what
india's response should be
the day china launches an invasion of
taiwan
india should immediately
act and secure nepal and bhutan
immediately that is what india should do
which means that indian army should be
in nepal and it should be
it should be guarding the northern
border of nepal with tibet
and the same goes with bhutan the moment
china launches an invasion of taiwan
india needs to put extensive military
boots on the ground in nepal and bhutan
to safeguard the integrity of these two
regions
it is essential india does that so that
will be an apt response for china
and it will be a reintegration of these
two territories with india because
bhutan
has china the chinese have their eyes on
they are already nibbling away bhutanese
territory
in nepal the chinese look at it as a
buffer state
if in the future they intend to invade
some part of india they may very well
come through nepal because that is
they think that india will least expect
that
so that could be part of their
calculations any
sane general would would basically do
that
would consider that as part of their war
games
so if or rather when taiwan is invaded
by china india needs to immediately
secure the territories of nepal and
bhutan with its army
that's what needs to happen and when it
comes to balochistan
pok aksai chin all that will come back
in due time
but india needs to start acting like a
major power india needs to start
investing
significantly in bolstering the
technological prowess and capabilities
of the army
and in it needs to invest greatly in a
much more expanded
air force and much more expanded navy
so all this needs to happen right now
soviet asks will there be any changes in
the map of asia in the next 50 years
like the formation of new countries or
the annexation of any country
definitely 100 the map of asia is going
to change
in the next decade two decades
definitely the next five decades
so what is going to happen there are two
possibilities two scenarios that we can
consider
the first scenario is that china
displaces the united states
as the global superpower if that happens
my friends
if china is allowed to succeed in this
ambition
then the map of asia will change in
which way
the chinese will definitely
engineer the disintegration of india
india will become fragmented
bengal will become part of bangladesh
kashmir may become part of
pakistan and tamil nadu southern states
mississip
this is what the chinese have been
writing about
for many decades they have been writing
this writing about this in chinese
language
publications military publications
for decades so this is what they have
been planning this is part of their
long-term
agenda and this is their ambition so if
the chinese are allowed to
ascend to global superpower status
this is unfortunately what will happen
on the other hand
if india
succeeds in emerging as a global power
on its in its own right
if india could find the leadership from
within
that will take it to a global power
status which is
definitely possible in the next 20 years
if that happens
then in the next 50 years nepal will be
part of india
tibet will be free china will be broken
up
pakistan will basically exist as
independent balochistan sindh
punjab parts of pakistan will be
reintegrated with pakistan with
afghanistan where they belong
afghanistan will be stable and secure
and peaceful
and eventually maybe within 100 years
the indian subcontinent may be united
under one political dispensation so
these are two scenarios
one is india is fragmented and china
takes over the world secondly china is
fragmented
tibet is free and india is able to
re-integrate various parts of the
subcontinent
and establish peace in at least this
region of the world
so these are two possible scenarios with
what's going to happen
it all depends solely
on the actions that the indian
leadership takes
in the next year in the next five years
next 10 years and next
20 years it all rests in the hands
of india's leadership and in the hands
of the indian people
it all depends on whom they elect as
india's leaders
so the next two decades are critical
pivotal for the for the future of asia
weibov asks whether the cod can
really do something on the ground level
or is it only for the time when things
get accelerated from china
will it be able to influence expanding
trade etc
military exercises okay so you are
asking about the relevance of the quad
the so-called quad what is the quad
and what is its relevance in the world
today
is it a military alliance is it an
economic alliance what exactly is the
quad
so the quad is one of those things the
quad is essentially a
lose-knit network of four
like-minded partners who are aiming at a
broader
purpose the quad is basically us
a loose alliance of india the united
states
japan and australia so this is a
lose-need network it is
not a formal military alliance and there
is a broader larger purpose
the broader purpose is to shape the
global order
during this age of transition this
pivotal decade
the 2020s because the world is evolving
very rapidly
this is an age of transition from a
unipolar world
to a multi-polar world or maybe again to
a unipolar world if the chinese take
over
so the uniting principles of the quad
are democracy
the rules based order and a free
open and inclusive indo-pacific region
so these are the united principles of
the quad
so recently we had a summit in march i
think and there were three significant
outcomes
firstly there was going to be this
cooperation on kovid 19 vaccine
production and india will be the hub of
this co-ignite in vaccine production
secondly there will be cooperation on
emerging technologies new technologies
and thirdly there will be cooperation on
mitigating climate
change so this third mitigating climate
change
resolution is basically about telling
the world that we are not an
china alliance we have a broader agenda
but
we do have naval exercises in the quad
so basically
we recently had the malabar exercises
exercise in which even the australians
were invited for the first time
usually it is india japan japan and the
us
so australia is now getting involved in
this and there is the possibility of a
quad plus
kind of structure in which canada will
get involved france
new zealand uk may also get involved so
it is a lose net
alliance the agenda is to
implement a restructuring of the global
supply chains
india will be a vaccine hub there will
be cooperation in technology and
biotechnology
and in various strategically significant
areas and
this alliance hopes to use the network
effect
and to enlist the support and
cooperation of other states
in maintaining a global rule-based order
and
the overall objective is to basically
prevent china from ascending to
superpower status that is definitely
there yes
so the quad is a core group of four
countries
that seeks to enlist the support and
cooperation of various other countries
in military as well as non-military
actions without
focusing on membership so you don't have
to become a member of the court you can
be a court plus member
or you don't even have to be associated
with the court by name and you can still
engage in cooperation
so we are building an alliance of
like-minded nations
to preserve what is the current global
order and to prevent china from
hijacking
and taking over the world so that is
what the quad is it is
by no means a military alliance there is
a military element especially a naval
element
so it will all depend on what is going
to be the future
what scenarios will emerge in the next
coming years within this decade
and that will in the long term shape
the form and direction that the quad
takes
vishal asks there is an organization of
islamic cooperation the oic with 57
countries
as its members so why don't other
countries form a similar organization on
religious lines
india can use its buddhist history as
leverage
well that's a very good question lots of
people have made this suggestion
and this could never happen as long as
india is a secular state that
rejects its hindu buddhist and dharmic
heritage so if you look at the indian
constitution
it rejects it doesn't make a single
mention of india's culture and
civilization
uh it has clauses that are is that are
that are explicitly hindu phobic
and the indian laws are all hindu phobic
many of them the indian government
policies are hindu phobic
only hindu temples are controlled and
their wealth is stolen other religions
can do whatever they want with their
religious structures and and places of
worship
so india is an explicitly hindu-phobic
nation india is the world's
most hindu-phobic nation actually so as
long as
india has this official constitution and
laws and
government policy that is so anti-hindu
and anti-dharmic
how can india ever enter into any such
alliance with other dharmic nations when
india is an anti-arabic nation
right so as long as india's constitution
stays in force as long as india remains
this
secular socialist country as long as the
indian government
continues with its anti-hindu policies
india can never ever be part of such an
alliance
if you look at thailand if you look at
other countries they are way more proud
of their
indian heritage of their hindu buddhist
heritage than india ever is
if you look at any olympic games you
have a march passed in the beginning
where every contingent wears the
national dress
their own national dress and showcases
their culture if you look at thailand if
you look at the various southeast asian
countries
you will show them displaying their
hindu and buddhist heritage
very proudly but if you see the indian
contingent they will be downplaying
their
indian heritage right so that is what
you see india is becoming deracinated
india is india has lost its its identity
its own identity india is lost indians
are confused
and the indian government is explicitly
explicitly anti-hindu
and anti-indian culture so as long as
this
scenario continues india there is no
this this uh proposed dharmic coalition
can never happen
which is a shame because india india
can be a cultural superpower in india
can bring a lot of nations together
be on the strength of its cultural and
religious heritage
so it is something that one hopes will
change soon
okay raghav asks what are the pillars of
soft power and what
and how can india become ones what you
mean is
how can india become a soft power
superpower or something
i always keep emphasizing the fact that
india needs to concentrate on hard power
not soft power because soft power is
pointless
without hard power on the other hand
soft power does have its uses so
what are the pillars of soft power soft
power is
all about culture it's all about
culture and india has the potential to
become a cultural
superpower and a tourism superpower on
the basis of its culture
india has everything india needs it has
a 10 000 plus year old history it has
the
oldest surviving culture in the world
the oldest surviving civilization
in the world the oldest surviving
religious traditions in the world
the oldest languages in the world it has
a vibrant
diverse culture every
i mean it has so much plurality and
locality
so many beautiful local manifestations
of the
overall culture so india has the
potential to become a tourism and
cultural superpower
overnight if the government of india
were to invest in these things
and of course india will have to
re-embrace its its dharmic roots for
this to happen
so the pillars of soft power are simply
culture
india needs to uh to improve its
standards of living
india needs to increase its per capita
gdp by increasing its overall gdp
india needs to restructure education and
governance and all that
but all the raw ingredients india needs
for becoming a cultural superpower are
already present in india it is
trivial to utilize this and leverage it
so it's very simple india just needs to
re-embrace its culture and flaunt it and
leverage it
to become a cultural superpower that's
all it takes it is there
for our taking if our government were to
wake up
so that is it for the questions i had
selected now let me take a few
live questions
after removing this question
so kailash asks with the
future death of the dalai lama in the
election of the next of the next dalai
lama
will that be the initial step towards
the possible war between india and china
well will there be an election for the
next dalai lama i think the dalai lama
has indicated
that he would like that to happen if if
i heard if i remember correctly
so maybe there will not be a
reincarnation thing maybe there will be
an election for the dalai lama in which
case you will have two parallel dalai
lamas one in india
and one in tibet so the chinese will
definitely try and pressurize india to
not go ahead with this election of the
dalai lama within the tibetan community
in india
so that could definitely become a point
of contention between india and china
whether it leads to a war or not
has to be seen it depends on how
powerful china is in the future
and how powerful india is in the future
so it is definitely a potential flash
point
for the future
i clicked on something else and this
came up
okay shashank asks do you think that we
should ever be concerned about the
reports being published
by the western think tanks about india
on things like freedom of speech etc
it is a matter of concern it is
basically an attempt to interfere
in the internal affairs of india india
needs to have a very strong
stance against this any publication that
indulges in such
in such activities needs to be disbarred
from entering india
basically you have these surveys and all
that that are being done
within within india right these
journalists
so-called journalists agenda-driven
people
they come to india they get they take
visas they come to india
they survey indian people
and then they take this data back to
wherever they came from
and put forth these distorted findings
my question is why is the indian
government
allowing such publications to
operate in india the chinese do not
tolerate any sort of anti-china activity
from any western publication on chinese
soil
if any western publication publishes
anti-china content
or news or opinions that publication is
banned from china and there are severe
repercussions so my question is why
doesn't the indian government have the
fortitude
to do the same it is a matter of grave
concern
it affects india's it affects the way
india is viewed globally
and it affects the the opinions of
people within india
especially youngsters who don't know
right from wrong because they don't have
enough information
so they look upon these bbcs and cnns
and washington post
etc as globally
reputable news sources and then they
believe all this about their country
so india the indian government needs to
have a more
proactive and more nationalistic
approach towards dealing with these
attempts
at regime change or at least at uh
interfering in india's internal affairs
definitely
good question so if christianity acted
as a barrier towards
innovation and freedom why do you think
the renaissance happened in europe while
the catholic church
still had a great amount of power
so there is one very important event
in europe that eventually
caused a great deal of change and this
event is the formation of the anglican
church
in england the english king henry viii
dissociated he he basically broke off
with the catholic church
he set up his own church the anglican
church which
was a protestant church and their
attitude was very different
they were they tolerated new information
they tolerated science
they tolerated technology they tolerated
progress
and it was under the regime of his
daughter
uh elizabeth that that england started
prospering
of course they it benefited greatly from
the amount of money that started coming
in from india
so it is this big change that that
basically propelled
england above every other european
nation in terms of scientific
and technological progress which
translated itself into geopolitical
progress
and therefore other nations in europe
had no
option but to follow suit now when it
comes to the so-called renaissance in
europe
it was basically all in
various italian city states that were
under the patronage of the
of the church but they were in some ways
independent in some kind or they
basically
were allowed to do this they also had a
great deal of ties with the ottomans
and they benefited a great deal a great
deal from the trade with the ottomans
so it is this strange accident of
history that led to the renaissance
and it is it happened at the time when
the power of the catholic
church had started declining when the
prestige of the catholic church had
started declining
so it coincide it coincides with that it
does coincide with that
and it is interesting that the this act
of henry viii
it basically set in motion a chain of
events that has led to what
we are in today the situation that
europe is in in today and the west is in
today
that basically christianity is in
terminal decline in the west
and the catholic church is being forced
to look east
and that's why they are investing
billions of dollars every year
in converting indians in large numbers
and if the indian government is
tolerating all that
okay let's take one more question for
today
something about world history or
geopolitics i hope
what is my opinion on afghanistan i just
gave my opinion sir
um
okay this is a good question after putin
loses control of russia what will be the
future of russia
will it be one state or will it break up
into several states
well this is hypothetical
will mr putin lose control of russia or
will he
eventually delegate his power to
somebody else remains to be seen
as of as of today he is the uh
he is essentially the emperor of russia
the tsar of russia
by another name and he is all powerful
in russia
but in the future if if mr putin does
lose control if he does
relinquish power to somebody else or
fall out of power because of some reason
there is a possibility of russia
breaking up the chinese will very much
want to engineer that
the chinese have their eyes on siberia
they have that eyes on reaching various
parts
of northern asia so yes the
russia and china are not really allies
they are
long-term geopolitical adversaries
so currently russia is very strong
because of mr putin
because of his iron-fisted rule in
russia as long as it continues china
will
treat russia with a great deal of
respect but in the future if somebody
else comes to power
and if that person is not as strong then
yes the chinese will want to
engineer a breakup of russia and that is
something mr putin must have already
calculated
because he is very much aware of the
very fraught history
that china and russia share
okay my friends that is it for today
thank you so much for your questions
thank you for participating
and i will see you in the next episode
thank you very much
have a good day have a good night i'll
see you tomorrow bye